mail: bruno.baere@gmail.com phone: +5521996826336

SUMMARY

I am motivated by challenging tasks and to teach others about what I have learned. My experience as both an academic researcher and as a systems analyst helps me to approach, to model, to understand problems, and to develop a solution. My analytical skills have been proven useful in detecting and preventing bugs and problems in systems modeling.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Technical Lead

Feb 2022 - Present

Instituto Tecgraf - PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

C++ lead developer in v3o2 project. Development and support of the software using modern C++.

Senior Systems Analyst

Feb 2020 - Feb 2022

Instituto Tecgraf – PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

C++ developer in v3o2 project. Programming in C++ 17 using Qt, GTK+, boost on Linux CentOS 7. Version control in git and CI/CD with gitlab. Worked in a remote (work from home) environment, using VPN and ssh, coordinating using Jira and Slack.

Product Owner Feb 2018 - Jan 2020

Instituto Tecgraf – PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

Product Owner in v3o2 project. Responsible for the product value of various parts of the software dealing with geology and geophysics. Responsibilities included: understand the client needs, propose a solution, create user stories for the development team, and manage client expectations. I also wrote and maintained the product manual for the parts I was responsible for, and helped restructuring the recruitment interview process.

Senior Systems Analyst / Researcher

Aug 2011 - Feb 2018

Instituto Tecgraf – PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

C++ developer in v3o2 project, a seismic and well data visualizer for Petrobras running on RedHat/CentOS 5 using OpenGL, GTK+, boost, and Qt. For QA used GoogleTest framework, valgrind, and cppcheck. I organized and wrote the documentation of the development environment setup for home office, and worked on the upgrade to RedHat/CentOS 6. I also presented with colleagues a 2 day workshop on Scrum for team members.

Researcher Apr 2009 - Aug 2011

ICAD/Visionlab - PUC-Rio

Researcher in games, digital entertainment and simulations. C# programmer in a joint project with CENPES and USP. Developed a shade tree editor in C# and Windows GDI for building DirectX shaders for the proof tank visualizer project.

Undergraduate teaching assistant

Mar 2009 - Dec 2009

Department of Computer Science - PUC-Rio

Worked as UTA for Introduction to Programming (C language) and Data Structures. Gave extra classes at Saturdays and post-class hours, resolving exercises and exams.

Intern Oct 2008 - Mar 2009

ICA - Laboratório de Inteligência Computacional Aplicada – PUC-Rio

C# developer. Worked at FxANEEL project, developing part of the user interface with WindowsForms and XML. Developed a wrapper for GSLIB library in C# and created the model for library documentation used by the lab.

Scientific Initiation

Aug 2006 - Aug 2008

ICAD/Visionlab - PUC-Rio

Development of a simulation library for Torque Game Engine. Researched game engine use in fluid simulations, programmed in C++ using OGRE rendering engine. Granted 2 years of CNPQ scholarship.

PUBLICATIONS

Maria das G. de A. Chagas, **Bruno B. P. L. de Araujo**, Waldecir V. Faria, Cezar G. Loureiro, Maria I. M. M. Carmo, Nelson J. Donato, Tathiana S. T. Silva, Victoria D. Maidantchik, Yann L. M. de M. Marques. *Design de Jogos de RPG Digitais: Uma investigação sobre a experiência de jogo*. In: Proceedings of XIV Brazilian Symposium on Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames 2015), Teresina, Piauí, Brazil, November 2015.

Paula C. Ribeiro, **Bruno B. P. L. de Araujo**, Alberto Raposo. *ComFiM: A Cooperative Serious Game to Encourage the Development of Communicative Skills between Children with Autism*. In: Proceedings of the XIII Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames 2014), Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil, November 2014. DOI: 10.1109/SBGAMES.2014.19

Bruno B. P. L. de Araujo, Bruno Feijó. *Evaluating dynamic difficulty adaptivity in shoot'em up games*. In: Proceedings of the XII Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames 2013), São Paulo, Brazil, October 2013.

EDUCATION

M.Sc. in Computer Science, Computer Graphics

2010 - 2012

Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro – PUC-Rio

Advisor: Bruno Feijó

Dissertation title: A study on dynamic difficulty adaptivity for shoot'em up games

Granted 2 years of CAPES scholarship

GPA/CR: 3.54 (4.0 scale) / 89%

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering

2005 - 2009

Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro – PUC-Rio

Minor: Advanced studies in Mathematics

Final project title: A shade tree editor for OGRE materials

Granted 2 years of CNPQ scholarship

Language proficiency: Cambridge English FCE grade B2

2003

EXTRA-CURRICULAR COURSES

Programming with Google Go Specialization
University of California, Irvine on Coursera, 24h.

2021

Data Science Math Skills

2021

Duke University on Coursera, 13h.

2020

Digital Product Management: Modern Fundamentals University of Virginia on Coursera, 16h.

| | Fundamentals of Project Planning and Management University of Virginia on Coursera, 8h. | 2018 |
|----------------------|--|----------------------------|
| | O setor de games no Brasil: panorama, carreiras e oport Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, 30h. | unidades 2018 |
| | Introduction to User Experience Design Georgia Institute of Technology on Coursera, 10h. | 2017 |
| | Gamification University of Pennsylvania on Coursera, 48h. | 2016 |
| | A complexidade sensível: Um paralelo entre videogames Universidade Estadual de Campinas on Coursera, 14h. | s e arte 2016 |
| | Oil & Gas Industry Operations and Markets Duke University on Coursera, 10h. | 2016 |
| | Geologia do petróleo para não-geólogos ABGP - Associação Brasileira de Geólogos do Petróleo, | 2014 20h. |
| CERTIFICATIONS | Certified Scrum Product Owner Certifier: Scrum Alliance License: 000304959 | Valid: Mar 2014 - Mar 2024 |
| | Certified Scrum Master Certifier: Scrum Alliance License: 000304959 | Valid: Jan 2014 - Mar 2024 |
| EXTRA- CURRICULAR | Co-organizer of PUC-Rio's Global Game Jam Helped organize PUC-Rio's Global Game Jam. | Jan 2018, Jan 2020 |
| ACTIVITIES | Volunteer reviewer for Entertainment Computing 2016 - Present Volunteer reviewer for Entertainment Computing, an Elsevier journal. ISSN 1875-9521. | |
| | Researcher at PUC-Rio's Game Design Research Group 2013 - Present Associate researcher in the Arts & Design Department research group under prof. Maria das Graças Chagas advisory. Themes include player-NPC relationship and artificial intelligence. | |
| | SBGames 2011's Independent Games Festival contestar Contestant with the game Lights Out. Awarded with the tin the Art Game cathegory. | |
| GAMES | Lights Out | 2011 |

Seu Espião Safado! 2011 A print-and-play dice game for 3 players where 2 agents are trying to uncover a spy's

Scripting Language) and 2D artist.

A puzzle-like art game for 2 players made in GameMaker 8.1. Presented at SBGames 2011, FILE Games 2012, Festival Games Brasil 2013. Role: programmer (GameMaker

secret (Brazilian Portuguese only). Role: game designer.

You Are Trash! 2009

A Java 2D game mix of puzzle and platformer, made in the Gamerama project. Role: programmer and game designer.

RPG

Encontros Aleatórios: O Bando da Pena Vermelha, In: Forbidden Magazine #12, Buró Brasil, 2021. Link

Encontros Aleatórios: A Estalagem Lebre Confortável, In: Forbidden Magazine #9, Buró Brasil, 2021. Link

Ser Mago pra Quê?, In: Forbidden Magazine #4, Buró Brasil, 2020. Link

Zen e a Arte de Armadilhas, In: Forbidden Magazine #2, Buró Brasil, 2020. Link

Delírios de X'agyg: Episódio 1 - A Balada de Baleem Altrafer, Editor: Rafael Beltrame, RedBox Editora, 2017. Link

OTHER INFORMATION

Personal homepage: http://killerasus.github.io